Guide to the Harry Roskolenko Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Harry Roskolenko collection
1933-1952
YCAL MSS 142
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.63
(2 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence and writings of American writer Harry Roskolenko. Correspondents include William Carlos Williams, Marianne Moore, Carl Sandburg, Katharine Anne Porter, John Dos Passos, Dwight Macdonald, William Saroyan, Wallace Stevens, Cleanth Brooks, Archibald MacLeish, Lewis Mumford, John Wheelwright, and James Laughlin, among other American poets, editors, critics, and publishers. Writings include a manuscript poem titled "Perfidious Albion," a typescript play titled "Journey of Five (Of Whom Three Were One)," and a typescript article, "What Poets Do For a Living (A Study of the Poet and his Predicament)." The article summarizes the results of an income survey that Roskolenko sent to fellow poets in April 1949, and is accompanied by response forms from 22 poets. These include Langston Hughes, William Carlos Williams, and Mark Van Doren.
Roskolenko, Harry, 1907-1980
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources as indicated on individual folders. The bulk of the letters were purchased on the George B. Alvord fund in 1952; the poet survey forms were purchased on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts and Letters fund in 1952; the manuscripts of the play and poem were the gift of S. R. Shapiro in 1953. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 2: Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
HARRY ROSKOLENKO (1907-1980)
Harry Roskolenko was born in New York City, the son of Ukrainian immigrants. He was a poet, a novelist, a foreign news correspondent, and a travel writer. He also wrote several volumes of autobiography, including a memoir about his childhood, When I Was Last on Cherry Street. After a life of extensive travel throughout the world, he died of cancer in New York.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence and writings of the American writer Harry Roskolenko, spanning the years 1933-51. It is organized into two series: Correspondence and Writings.
Series I, Correspondence, is arranged alphabetically, and contains correspondence from publishers, poetry reviews and literary magazines, and many prominent American poets and other writers of the mid-twentieth century, including William Carlos Williams, Marianne Moore, Carl Sandburg, Katherine Anne Porter, John Dos Passos, Dwight Macdonald, William Saroyan, Wallace Stevens, Cleanth Brooks, Archibald MacLeish, Lewis Mumford, John Wheelwright, Thomas Mann, and George Orwell. There are also letters from Edmund Wilson and Lionel Trilling.
Because this list was compiled from previously existing catalog cards, all correspondents are listed by name rather than by affiliation. However, the majority write on behalf of a publisher or publication. For example, James Laughlin writes as publisher of New Directions; Edmund Wilson, Bruce Bliven, and Nigel Forbes Dennis write as editors of The New Republic; and Peter DeVries, Karl Shapiro, Harriet Monroe, George Dillon and Morton Zabel all write on behalf of Poetry. Other publishers and publications represented in the correspondence are The New York Times, Houghton Mifflin, Doubleday, Henry Holt, Pulse, Common Sense, and The Sewanee Review, among others.
Series II, Writings, contains three manuscripts. These are a manuscript poem titled "Perfidious Albion!," a typescript play, Journey of Five (Of Whom Three Were One), and a typescript article, "What Poets Do For a Living (A Study of the Poet and his Predicament)," which was published in Plain Talk. The article summarizes the results of an income survey that Roskolenko sent to fellow poets in April 1949, and is accompanied by the survey response forms from twenty-two poets. These include Langston Hughes, William Carlos Williams, and Mark Van Doren.
Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Wages -- United States -- Poets; Writers, American -- 20th Century; Poets -- United States; Brooks, Cleanth, 1906-1994; Dos Passos, John, 1896-1970; Hughes, Langston, 1902-1967; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997; Macdonald, Dwight, 1906-1982; MacLeish, Archibald, 1892-1982; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980; Roskolenko, Harry, 1907-1980; Sandburg, Carl, 1878-1967; Saroyan, William, 1908-1981; Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972; Wheelwright, John, 1897-1940; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963
- Correspondence, 1933-51; Series I; 73
  - Adams, James Donald, 1939 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alsberg, Henry G. (Henry Garfield), 1940 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Benét, Stephen Vincent, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bliven, Bruce, 1943 Jun 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Breit, Harvey, 1948 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Brinnin, John Malcolm, 1935-36 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brooks, Cleanth, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Céline, Louis-Ferdinand (Destouches), 1935 Nov 21 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Chamberlain, John, 1951 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Crichton, Kyle Samuel, 1933 Dec 20 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Damon, S. Foster (Samuel Foster), 1934 Dec 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Dennis, Nigel Forbes, 1941 Dec 19 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - De Vries, Peter, 1936-42 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Scope and Contents
    With letter from Roskolenko 1942 Jan 27
  - Dillon, George, 1939 Jan 28 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dos Passos, John, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Eastman, Max Forrester, 1934 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Elder, Donald B., 1948 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Farrar, John Chipman, 1948 Jan 29 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Farrell, James T. (James Thomas), 1942-44 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fearing, Kenneth, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ford, Charles Henri, 1939-40 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Foujita, Tsugouharu, 1947-49 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Gosling, Glenn, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Hicks, Granville, 1940-52 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Hillyer, Robert Silliman, 1949 Jun 19 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Hutchens, John K., 1951 Dec 13 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Jarrell, Randall, 1941 Aug 8 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Jolas, Eugene, 1936 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Laughlin, James, 1938-41 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Leggett, John, 1950 Aug 23 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Levine, Isaac Don, 1949 Sep 7 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Lovett, Robert Morss, 1941-43 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Macdonald, Dwight, [1939] May 30 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - MacLeish, Archibald, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mann, Thomas, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Marshall, Margaret, 1939, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Mason, James, 1947 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Merz, Charles, 1951 Oct 9 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Monroe, Harriet, 1931-35 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Moore, Marianne, 1939 Jul 27 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Mumford, Lewis, 1938-48 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    Letter of 1938 Nov 26 encloses corrected typescript of a comment on Roskolenko's poems, signed and dated Nov 27, 1938
  - Munson, Gorham Bert, 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    With TLS to Donald Thompson referring to HR, and typed copy of a "Foreword" for HR's poems
  - Orwell, George Orwell, Sonia, 1949 Dec (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Palmer, John Edwin, 1947 Oct 18 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Patchen, Kenneth, 1938-39 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Payne, Robert, n.y. Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Pearce, Charles Albert, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1940 Sep 13 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Ransom, John Crowe, n.y. Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Read, Herbert Edward, Sir, 1946 Oct 14 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Rexroth, Kenneth, 1948, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Riding, Laura, 1939 Feb 12 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Rodman, Selden, 1941-42 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Rorby, James, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Rosenfeld, Paul, 1935-41 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Rovere, Richard Halworth, 1943 Mar 25 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Sandburg, Carl, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Saroyan, William, 1939 Apr 28 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Shapiro, Karl Jay, 1950-51 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Stevens, Wallace, 1938 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Summers, Mrs. U. T., 1948 Jul 8 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Swallow, Alan, 1951 Feb 14 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Tate, Allen, 1945 Mar 16 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Trilling, Lionel, 1948 Jul 7 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Untermeyer, Louis, 1940 Aug 12 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Van Doren, Irita Bradford, 1939, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Van Gelder, Robert, 1945 Jun (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Walker, Ann, 1939, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Wheelwright, John, 1938-39 (Box 1, Folder 69)
    Some of the letters have typed poems on their versos
  - Williams, William Carlos, 1934-49 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1938-41 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Zabel, Morton Dauwen, 1937 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Zaturenska, Marya, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Zukofsky, Louis, 1930-31 (Box 1, Folder 74)
- Writings, 1948-[51]; Series II; 27
  - Journey of the Five (Of Whom Three were One), typescript mimeograph play, [1951] (Box 1, Folder 75)
    "A dramatic verse play establishing and examining certain motives, elements, and attitudes of a poet best known as Thomas Stearns Eliot." Read at a T.S. Eliot evening, Oxford poetry society, Fall 1951
  - "Perfidious Albion!," manuscript poem, 1948 Mar 7 (Box 1, Folder 76)
    Written for S. R. Shapiro
  - "What Poets Do For a Living (A Study of the Poet and his Predicament)"
    - Typescript carbon of article, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 77)
      With rejection letter from The Saturday Review of Literature
    - Blank survey form and cover letter with list of participants on verso, 1949 Apr 3 (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Survey Responses
      - Chisolm, Hugh, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 79)
      - Creekmore, Hubert, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 80)
      - Eberhart, Richard, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 81)
      - Fearing, Kenneth, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 82)
        Typed letter
      - Goodman, Paul, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 83)
      - Griffin, Howard, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 84)
        With autograph letter
      - Holden, Raymond P., [1949] (Box 1, Folder 85)
      - Holmes, John Clellon, 1949 Apr 9 (Box 1, Folder 86)
        Typed letter, with additional, unrelated letter 1949 Apr 5
      - Hughes, Langston, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 87)
        With carbon copy of Hughes' curriculum vitae
      - Humphries, Rolfe, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 88)
      - Ignatow, David, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 89)
        With separate "Statement of Motives" and "Description of Living Conditions"
      - Kees, Weldon, 1949 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 90)
        Autograph letter
      - Nims, John Frederick, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 91)
      - Moss, Howard, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 92)
      - Raiziss, Sona (Sonia), [1949] (Box 1, Folder 93)
        With typed note
      - Rexroth, Kenneth, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 94)
      - Schwartz, Selwyn S., 1949 Apr 7 (Box 1, Folder 95)
      - Scott, Winfield Townley, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 96)
      - Van Doren, Mark, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 97)
      - Vazakas, Byron, 1949 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 98)
      - Viereck, Peter Robert Edwin, [1949] (Box 1, Folder 99)
      - Villa, Jose Garcia, 1949 Apr 4 (Box 1, Folder 100)
        Typed note from HR, with autograph note in reply from Villa on same leaf
      - Williams, William Carlos, 1949 Apr 5 (Box 1, Folder 101)
        With typed letter
- Restricted Fragile, 7
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 43 (Box 2, Folder 102)
  - Box 1, folder 55 (Box 2, Folder 103)
  - Box 1, folder 69 (Box 2, Folder 104)
  - Box 1, folder 70 (Box 2, Folder 105)
  - Box 1, folder 73 (Box 2, Folder 106)
  - Box 1, folder 78 (Box 2, Folder 107)
  - Box 1, folder 89 (Box 2, Folder 108)